# Musa J. Taib

J 403 805 7753 ▼ Musajabbartaib@gmail.com 🛅 Linkedin.com/in/musajtaib/ 🕥 github.com/MusajTaib

# Summary

Recent Master's graduate specialized in Machine Learning and Data Science, bringing over three years of research experience in the field. Currently working as a Machine Learning and Data Researcher, I am actively seeking opportunities to further my career in the fields of Data Science and Machine Learning.

## Experience

### University of Calgary

Sept 2023 - Present

Machine Learning and Data Reseacher

Calgary, Canada

- Developed secure, privacy-focused ML models in **PyTorch** using federated learning with differential privacy for on-site applications, including homelessness trend analysis. This involved advanced time series analysis for data pattern identification in collaboration with local agencies.
- Authored multiple scholarly papers and conference abstracts and presented research at multiple forums to academic and general audiences.

# University of Calgary

Sept 2021 - August 2023

Teaching and Machine Learning Research Assistant

Calgary, Canada

- As an RA: Spearheaded a large-scale data analysis initiative by processing and analyzing 200 GB of administrative health data for different databases for both structured and unstructured data, recommending resource allocation for over 100,000 clients.
- Executed complex data cleaning and engineering of time series health data into structured temporal matrices for enhanced feature extraction, utilized Seaborn, Matplotlib and Statsmodel in Python for intricate EDA and data visualization and used MySQL for robust database management.
- Devised an innovative algorithm for multivariate time series data using dynamic time warping for feature ranking based on effective temporal resolution, reducing matrix sizes by 70% and preserving 95% of model performance.
- Enhanced processing throughout and model training scalability by integrating Compute Canada's ARC HPC capabilities using shell scripting.
- Conducted comprehensive cross-validation on heterogeneous ML models (implemented using **TensorFlow**), achieving a 12% performance boost, thereby affirming the method's robustness and generalizability across varied architectures.
- As a TA: Led labs covering topics from machine learning to network protocols, mentored student project teams towards capstone readiness, administered technical exams, and led undergrad teams with a focus on engineering project management.

## Robotics and Machine Intelligence (ROMI) Lab

June 2020 - June 2021

Data Science Research Intern

Islamabad. Pakistan

- Mined data and made NLP models using PyTorch, integrating GANs to synthesize authentic-feeling network traffic, successfully mimicking patterns from high-traffic platforms like YouTube, Facebook, and Dailymotion.
- Streamlined data analysis and operational efficiency by leveraging shell scripting in Linux, coupled with strategic application of clustering algorithms for enhanced anomaly detection and network security insights.

#### Technical Skills

Languages: Python, Java, C++, C, Linux shell scripting, SQL, MATLAB, Latex.

Libraries & Frameworks: Pandas, NumPy, PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras, SciPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Imbalanced Learn, SciKit Learn, Spacy, NLTK, Statsmodels, OpenCV.

Technologies: Linux, Git, MySQL, HPC, AWS, Dockers, SageMaker, Excel, Power BI, ETL.

ML Expertise: Deep Learning (CNNs, RNNs), Federated Learning, Regression, Classification, Clustering, Time series analysis, Data Transformation and Optimization.

#### Education

# University of Calgary

Sep. 2021 - Nov. 2023

Masters of Science in Electrical Engineering (CGPA: 4.0/4.0)

Calgary, Alberta

### National University of Sciences and Technology

Sep. 2017 - Jun. 2021

Bachelors of Engineering in Electrical Engineering (CGPA: 3.65/4.0)(Minor in Business Studies)

Calgary, Alberta

## Projects

### Mortality Prediction using SAPS-2 Features

2022 - Present

- Orchestrated an ETL pipeline on Amazon S3, managing the vast MIMIC-III database (over 40,000 patients), enhancing data retrieval and storage scalability while ensuring integrity. Employed unsupervised learning for astute feature discernment.
- Engineered and refined predictive models with GRUs, SVMs and Random forests, realizing an AUC-ROC of 85%, demonstrating potent precision in foreseeing patient prognoses within the extensive dataset.

### CGANs for Data Augmentation

2022

- Implemented a CNN-based Conditional GAN for data augmentation on MNIST, FashionMNIST and CIFAR-10, generating synthetic images to counteract class imbalance.
- Optimized model performance with HPC-driven parallel job arrays, enhancing F1-Score by 10%.